I just heard the best joke about Bond Emeruwa.
لقد سمعت حالا نكتة رائعة عن "بوند إيميروا".
I was having lunch with him just a few minutes ago,
كنت أتناول الغذاء معه منذ قليل
and a Nigerian journalist comes -- and this will only make sense
ثم أتى صحفي نيجيري-- وهذا سيكون مفهوما فقط
if you've ever watched a James Bond movie --
لمن شاهد أحد أفلام "جيمس بوند"
and a Nigerian journalist comes up to him and goes,
ثم اتى الصحفي النيجيري إليه قائلا:
"Aha, we meet again, Mr. Bond!"
"اهااا, نلتقي مجددا,سيد "بوند" !! "
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It was great.
ياه, كانت رائعة.
So, I've got a little sheet of paper here,
حسنا, لدي تلك القطعة الصغيرة من الورق هنا,
mostly because I'm Nigerian and if you leave me alone,
في الأغلب لأنني نيجيري, و لو تركتموني أتحدث
I'll talk for like two hours.
سوف أستمر في الحديث لساعتين.
I just want to say good afternoon, good evening.
ولكن فقط أريد ان اقول مساء الخير.
It's been an incredible few days.
الأيام السابقة كانت رائعاً.
It's downhill from now on. I wanted to thank Emeka and Chris.
و من الان فصاعدا ستبدأ في التنازل. أريد أن أشكر "إيميكا" و "كريس".
But also, most importantly, all the invisible people behind TED
و لكن الأهم ايضا كل هؤلاء العاملين في الخلفية
that you just see flitting around the whole place
الذين ترونهم يتنقلون في سرية حول المكان
that have made sort of this space for such a diverse and robust conversation.
ليعطونا تلك المساحة للحديث القوي و المتنوع.
It's really amazing.
شئ رائع حقا.
I've been in the audience.
ولقد كنت جالسا وسط المستمعين.
I'm a writer, and I've been watching people with the slide shows
أنا كاتب, وكنت أراقب المتحدثين و هم يستخدمون شرائح عرض
and scientists and bankers, and I've been feeling a bit
و علماء و مصرفيين و لقد جعلني هذا أشعر
like a gangsta rapper at a bar mitzvah.
كأنني مغني راب من أحد العصابات يجلس في "إحتفال البلوغ" اليهودي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Like, what have I got to say about all this?
فماذا أستطيع أن اقول مع كل هذا؟
And I was watching Jane [Goodall] yesterday,
و عندما كنت أشاهد حديث "جاين جودال" البارحة,
and I thought it was really great, and I was watching
و أعتقد انها كانت رائعة, و كنت أجلس متابعا
those incredible slides of the chimpanzees, and I thought,
صور حيوانات الشمبانزي الرائعة التي عرضتها , و فكرت
"Wow. What if a chimpanzee could talk, you know? What would it say?"
"ياه ماذا لو إستطاع الشمبانزي أن يتكلم, ماذا كان سيقول؟"
My first thought was, "Well, you know, there's George Bush."
و أول ما خطر لي كان " حسنا و ماذا عن جورج بوش؟"
But then I thought, "Why be rude to chimpanzees?"
ثم فكرت, "و لكن لماذا نسُب الشمبانزي؟"
I guess there goes my green card.
ها قد إنتهى الكارت الأخضر خاصتي!
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
There's been a lot of talk about narrative in Africa.
كان هناك الكثير من النقاش حول التراث القصصي لأفريقيا.
And what's become increasingly clear to me is that
و الذي يزداد وضوحا بالنسبة لي أننا
we're talking about news stories about Africa;
نتحدث عن قصص الأخبار "عن" أفريقيا ؛
we're not really talking about African narratives.
لسنا نتحث عن القصص الأفريقية الأصل.
And it's important to make a distinction, because if the news is anything to go by,
و لابد هنا من التفرقة بين التعريفين, لأننا لو إعتمدنا على الأخبار
40 percent of Americans can't -- either can't afford health insurance
عندما تقول 40% من الأمريكان إما لا يتحملون تكلفة التأمين الصحي
or have the most inadequate health insurance,
أو لديهم تأمين صحي ولكن غير مؤثر,
and have a president who, despite the protest
و أن لديهم رئيس , برغم كل المعارضات
of millions of his citizens -- even his own Congress --
لملايين من مواطنيه--حتى من الكونجرس--
continues to prosecute a senseless war.
يستمر في شن حرب بدون معنى.
So if news is anything to go by,
إذن لو إعتمدنا على الأخبار
the U.S. is right there with Zimbabwe, right?
لوضعنا الولايات المتحدة في نفس الفئة السياسية مع زيمبابوي, أليس كذلك؟
Which it isn't really, is it?
وهو ليس ما عليه الواقع بالطبع, أليس كذلك؟
And talking about war, my girlfriend has this great t-shirt
و بمناسبة الحديث عن الحرب--صديقتي لديه قميص رائع
that says, "Bombing for peace is like fucking for virginity."
مكتوب عليه, "قصف القنابل من أجل السلام هو مثل المضاجعة للوصول إلى العذرية."
It's amazing, isn't it?
رائع, أليس كذلك؟
The truth is, everything we know about America,
الحقيقة هي, أن الأمريكان و كل ما نعرفه عن الأمريكان,
everything Americans come to know about being American,
كل ما يعرفه الأمريكان نفسهم عن كونهم أمريكان,
isn't from the news.
لا يأتي من الأخبار.
I live there.
لقد عشت هناك.
We don't go home at the end of the day and think,
فنحن لا نعود إلى البيت في نهاية اليوم مفكرين
"Well, I really know who I am now
" حسنا الآن انا أعرف هويتي الحقيقية
because the Wall Street Journal says that the Stock Exchange
من صحيفة وال ستريت التي تقول أن تبادل الأسهم "
closed at this many points."
قد أغلق في تلك الأماكن العديدة."
What we know about how to be who we are comes from stories.
ما نعرفه عن كيف أصبحنا ما نحن عليه يأتي من القصص.
It comes from the novels, the movies, the fashion magazines.
يأتي من الروايات, الأفلام, مجلات الموضة
It comes from popular culture.
يأتي من الثقافة العامة.
In other words, it's the agents of our imagination
بكلمات أخرى, إنها عوامل من خيالنا
who really shape who we are. And this is important to remember,
هي التي تشكل ما نحن عليه. وهو شئ من المهم تَذكُره
because in Africa
لأننا في أفريقيا
the complicated questions we want to ask about
كل الأسئلة المعقدة التي نريد أن نسألها
what all of this means has been asked
عن معنى كل تلك الأشياء--قد سُألت بالفعل--
from the rock paintings of the San people,
من رسومات قوم ال"سان" على الحوائط الحجرية ,
through the Sundiata epics of Mali, to modern contemporary literature.
إلى ملحمات "سندياتا" في مالي, إلى الأدب الحديث المعاصر.
If you want to know about Africa, read our literature --
فإذا أرتدم ان تعرفوا عن أفريقيا, إقرأوا الأدب الأفريقي
and not just "Things Fall Apart," because that would be like saying,
و ليس فقط رواية "كل شئ يتداعى" لأن ذلك كأنك تقول
"I've read 'Gone with the Wind' and so I know everything about America."
"لقد قرأت (ذهب مع الريح) إذن فإني أعرف كل شئ عن أمريكا"
That's very important.
هذا شئ مهم جدا.
There's a poem by Jack Gilbert called "The Forgotten Dialect of the Heart."
هناك قصيدة كتبها "جاك جيلبيرت" تدعى "لغة القلب المنسية"
He says, "When the Sumerian tablets were first translated,
يقول :"عندما ترجمت الألواح السومرية لأول مرة,
they were thought to be business records.
قالوا أنها قد تكون تسجيلات تجارية
But what if they were poems and psalms?
ولكن ماذا لو كانت قصائد و ترانيم؟
My love is like twelve Ethiopian goats
تقول إن حبي لك مثل إثنى عشرة عنزة إثيوبية
standing still in the morning light.
تقف بثبات في نور الصباح.
Shiploads of thuja are what my body wants to say to your body.
يبعث جسدي إلى جسدك سفن محملة بأشجار الحياة.
Giraffes are this desire in the dark."
و الزراف هو تلك الرغبة الكامنة في الظلمات"
This is important.
هذا حقا مهم.
It's important because misreading is really the chance
إنه مهم لأن القراءة الخاطئة تعطي فرصة
for complication and opportunity.
للتعقيد
The first Igbo Bible was translated from English
أول إنجيل بلغة الإجبو كان مترجما من الإنجليزية
in about the 1800s by Bishop Crowther,
في حوالي القرن الثامن عشر, و ترجمه الأسقف "كراوثر"
who was a Yoruba.
و قد كان من جماعة عرقية تدعى "يوروبا".
And it's important to know Igbo is a tonal language,
و يجب أن تعرفوا أن لغة الإجبو لغة تعتمد على النبرة,
and so they'll say the word "igwe" and "igwe":
فمثلا يقولون "إجواي" و "إجواي"
same spelling, one means "sky" or "heaven,"
نفس الهجاء , واحدة تعني "سماء"
and one means "bicycle" or "iron."
و الأخرى تعني "دراجة" أو "حديد"
So "God is in heaven surrounded by His angels"
إذن "الرب في السماء محاط بملائكته"
was translated as --
ترجمت إلى---
[Igbo].
[لغة إجبو]
And for some reason, in Cameroon, when they tried
ولسبب ما, في الكاميرون, عندما حاولوا
to translate the Bible into Cameroonian patois,
ترجمة الإنجيل إلى اللغة العامية الكاميرونية,
they chose the Igbo version.
إختاروا النسخة الإجبوية.
And I'm not going to give you the patois translation;
ولن أقولها باللهجة العامية (الكاميرونية)
I'm going to make it standard English.
سأقولها بلإنجليزية العادية
Basically, it ends up as "God is on a bicycle with his angels."
توصلوا لى ترجمته هكذا: " الرب على دراجة محاطا بملائكته."
This is good, because language complicates things.
وهذا شئ جيد لأن اللغة تعقد الأشياء.
You know, we often think that language mirrors
أتعلمون, عادة ما نقول أن اللغة تعكس
the world in which we live, and I find that's not true.
العالم الذي نعيش فيه, و أنا لا أعتقد أن هذا صحيح.
The language actually makes the world in which we live.
اللغة في الحقيقة "تصنع" العالم الذي نعيش فيه.
Language is not -- I mean, things don't have
اللغة ليست--أعني الأشياء لا تعطي
any mutable value by themselves; we ascribe them a value.
لأنفسها أي قيمة متغيرة, نحن ننسب إليها القيمة.
And language can't be understood in its abstraction.
و اللغة لا يمكن فهمها في صورتها التجريدية.
It can only be understood in the context of story,
يمكن فقط فهمها في سياق القصة
and everything, all of this is story.
وكل شئ حولنا, كل هذا ما هو إلا قصة.
And it's important to remember that,
ومن المهم أن نتذكر هذا
because if we don't, then we become ahistorical.
لإننا إن لم نفعل, سنصبح بدون تاريخ.
We've had a lot of -- a parade of amazing ideas here.
إن لدينا العديد بل موكب من الأفكار الرائعة هنا,
But these are not new to Africa.
و لكنها ليست بجديدة على أفريقيا.
Nigeria got its independence in 1960.
حصلت نيجيريا على إستقلالها في عام 1960.
The first time the possibility for independence was discussed
أول مرة طرحت فكرة الاستقلال للمناقشة
was in 1922, following the Aba women's market riots.
كانت في عام 1922, بعد ثورة نساء "أبا" ضد الضرائب.
In 1967, in the middle of the Biafran-Nigerian Civil War,
في 1967, وسط الحرب الأهلية بين نيجيريا و مقاطعة بيافرا,
Dr. Njoku-Obi invented the Cholera vaccine.
طور "د.نجوكو أوبي" لقاح الكوليرا.
So, you know, the thing is to remember that
إذن فمن المهم أن نتذكر,
because otherwise, 10 years from now,
لأن إذا لم نفعل, 10 سنوات من الآن,
we'll be back here trying to tell this story again.
سنعود إلى هنا مرة أخرى لنعيد ذكر تلك القصة.
So, what it says to me then is that it's not really --
إذن الذي أستخرجه من هذا, أن المشكلة ليست
the problem isn't really the stories that are being told
ليست في القصص التي نحكيها
or which stories are being told,
أو "أي" قصص نحكيها؛
the problem really is the terms of humanity
المشكلة تكمن في الجوانب الإنسانية
that we're willing to bring to complicate every story,
التي نحن على إستعداد لإدخالها لتعقيد كل قصة,
and that's really what it's all about.
وهذا هو المغزى من كل هذا.
Let me tell you a Nigerian joke.
دعوني أخبركم نكتة نيجيرية.
Well, it's just a joke, anyway.
حسنا إنها نكتة على أي حال.
So there's Tom, Dick and Harry and they're working construction.
هناك ثلاثة رجال "توم", "ديك" و "هاري" وهم يعملون في البناء.
And Tom opens up his lunch box and there's rice in it,
يفتح "توم" صندوق غذائه و يجد فيه أرز,
and he goes on this rant about, "Twenty years,
فيتشدق قائلا , "عشرون عاما
my wife has been packing rice for lunch.
و زوجتي تضع لي أرزا للغذاء.
If she does it again tomorrow, I'm going to throw myself
ولو كررت ذلك غدا, سألقي بنفسي
off this building and kill myself."
من فوق هذا المبنى لأموت."
And Dick and Harry repeat this.
و يكرر "ديك" و "هاري" نفس الكلام.
The next day, Tom opens his lunchbox, there's rice,
في اليوم التالي يفتح "توم" صندوق الغذاء و يجد أرز,
so he throws himself off and kills himself,
فيلقي بنفسه و يموت,
and Tom, Dick and Harry follow.
و يتبعه "ديك" و "هاري".
And now the inquest -- you know, Tom's wife
و في التحقيق, زوجة توم
and Dick's wife are distraught.
و زوجة ديك كانتا شديدتا الحزن.
They wished they'd not packed rice.
و تمنوا لو لم تضعا أرزا للغداء.
But Harry's wife is confused, because she said, "You know,
و لكن زوجة "هاري" كانت محتارة و قالت, " لقد كان
Harry had been packing his own lunch for 20 years."
هاري يعبأ طعامه بنفسه كل يوم لمدة 20 عاما."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
This seemingly innocent joke, when I heard it as a child in Nigeria,
هذه النكتة البريئة ظاهريا, عندما سمعتها و أنا طفل في نيجيريا,
was told about Igbo, Yoruba and Hausa,
قيلت عن واحد من الإجبو ، و اخر من اليوروبا و الثالث من الهاوسا
with the Hausa being Harry.
و هاري هو الهاوساوي.
So what seems like an eccentric if tragic joke about Harry
إذا فهذه النكتة التي تبدو غريبة و مأسوية بالنسبة ل"هاري"
becomes a way to spread ethnic hatred.
أصبحت وسيلة لنشر الكراهية و التفرقة العرقية.
My father was educated in Cork, in the University of Cork, in the '50s.
تعلم والدي في كورك, في جامعة كورك في الخمسينيات
In fact, every time I read in Ireland,
في الواقع كلما قرأت هذا في ايرلاندا
people get me all mistaken and they say,
يخطأ الناس هناك و يقولون,
"Oh, this is Chris O'Barney from Cork."
"أها هذا هو "كريس أوبارني" من كورك"
But he was also in Oxford in the '50s,
ولكنه كان أيضا في أكسفورد في الخمسينات
and yet growing up as a child in Nigeria,
و مع ذلك و انا طفل في نيجيريا
my father used to say to me, "You must never eat or drink
كان أبي يقول لي, "يجب الا تأكل أو تشرب أبدا
in a Yoruba person's house because they will poison you."
في بيت شخص "يوروبي" لأنه سيدسوا لك سم."
It makes sense now when I think about it,
و عندما أفكر في هذا الآن يصبح مفهوما أكثر
because if you'd known my father,
لأنكم إذا عرفتم والدي
you would've wanted to poison him too.
لأنكم إذا عرفتم أبي لأردتم أن تضعوا له السم أيضا!
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So I was born in 1966, at the beginning
لقد ولدت عام 1966 ,في بدايات
of the Biafran-Nigerian Civil War, and the war ended after three years.
الحرب الأهلية و أنتهت الحرب بعدها بثلاث سنوات.
And I was growing up in school and the federal government
و لقد كبرت في مدرسة حيث لم ترغب الحكومة الفيديرالية
didn't want us taught about the history of the war,
أن نتعلم عن تاريخ الحرب,
because they thought it probably would make us
لأنهم ظنوا في الأغلب أنها ستجعلنا
generate a new generation of rebels.
نخرج جيلا جديدا من الثوار.
So I had a very inventive teacher, a Pakistani Muslim,
و لكن كان لدي مدرس مبدع, كان باكستاني مسلم,
who wanted to teach us about this.
أراد أن يعلمنا عن الحرب.
So what he did was to teach us Jewish Holocaust history,
فماذا فعل, أخبرنا عن تاريخ محرقة اليهود,
and so huddled around books with photographs of people in Auschwitz,
فأخذ في تجميع كتب مليئة بصور للناس في "أوشفيتز",
I learned the melancholic history of my people
إذا فقد تعلمت التاريخ الكئيب لشعبي
through the melancholic history of another people.
من خلال التاريخ الكئيب لشعب آخر.
I mean, picture this -- really picture this.
أعني, تصوروا--حقا تخيلوا
A Pakistani Muslim teaching Jewish Holocaust history
معلم مسلم باكستاني يدرس تاريخ المحرقة اليهودية
to young Igbo children.
لأطفال صغار من الأيجبو.
Story is powerful.
القصة شئ قوي ذو نفوذ.
Story is fluid and it belongs to nobody.
القصة سلسة و لا تنتمي إلى أحد.
And it should come as no surprise
و لا يجب أن يفاجئكم إذن
that my first novel at 16 was about Neo-Nazis
أن أول رواية لي في سن ال16 كانت عن نازيين جدد
taking over Nigeria to institute the Fourth Reich.
يستولون على نيجيريا و يؤسسوا الرايخ الرابع.
It makes perfect sense.
شئ مفهوم جدا.
And they were to blow up strategic targets
و في القصة قذفوا و دمروا أهداف إستراتيجية
and take over the country, and they were foiled
وإحتلوا البلاد, ثم أحبط مخططاتهم
by a Nigerian James Bond called Coyote Williams,
شبيه نيجيري ل"جايمس بوند" يدعى "كويوتي ويليامز",
and a Jewish Nazi hunter.
و يهودي, يهودي يصيد النازيين
And it happened over four continents.
و جرت أحداثها عبر أربعة قارات.
And when the book came out, I was heralded as Africa's answer
و عندما نشر الكتاب, عظموني كالرد الأفريقي
to Frederick Forsyth, which is a dubious honor at best.
على "فريديرك فورسايث", و هو في أحسن الأحوال شرف مشكوك فيه.
But also, the book was launched in time for me to be accused
و لكن أيضا جاء وقت نشر الكتاب في الوقت الذي إتهموني فيه
of constructing the blueprint for a foiled coup attempt.
بوضع مخطط لمحاولة إنقلاب محبطة.
So at 18, I was bonded off to prison in Nigeria.
إذن في سن ال18, تم إقتيادي إلى السجن في نيجيريا.
I grew up very privileged, and it's important
و لقد تربيت ميسور الحال جدا, ومن المهم
to talk about privilege, because we don't talk about it here.
أن نتحدث عن هذه الإمتيازات, لأننا لا نلتفت إليها هنا
A lot of us are very privileged.
معظمنا ميسوري الحال بشكل كبير
I grew up -- servants, cars, televisions, all that stuff.
و لقد كبرت محاطا بالخدم و العربات و التلفزيونات و كل هذا
My story of Nigeria growing up was very different from the story
و قصتي عن نيجيريا و أنا أكبر, مختلفة تماما عن القصة
I encountered in prison, and I had no language for it.
التي لاقيتها في السجن, و لم تكن لدي اللغة لأوصفها.
I was completely terrified, completely broken,
لقد كنت مرعوبا تماما, مكسورا
and kept trying to find a new language,
و ظلت أحاول لأجد لغة جديدة,
a new way to make sense of all of this.
طريقة جديدة لأجد معنى لكل ما يحدث لي.
Six months after that, with no explanation,
بعد ذلك بستة أشهر, و بدون تفسير
they let me go.
أطلقوا سراحي.
Now for those of you who have seen me at the buffet tables know
و لمن منكم الذين رأوني على مائدة البوفيه يعرفون
that it was because it was costing them too much to feed me.
إن السبب في الأغلب كان أن إطعامي كان يكلفهم الكثير.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But I mean, I grew up with this incredible privilege,
و لكن انا أعني, لقد كبرت مع كل تلك الإمتيازات الرائعة,
and not just me -- millions of Nigerians
و لست انا فقط بل ملايين النيجيريين
grew up with books and libraries.
كبروا وسط الكتب و المكتبات.
In fact, we were talking last night about how all
في الواقع لقد كنا نتحدث بالأمس عن كيف ان كل
of the steamy novels of Harold Robbins
الروايات المثيرة ل"هارولد روبينز"
had done more for sex education of horny teenage boys in Africa
قد فعلت في مجال تعليم الجنس للأولاد المراهقين في أفريقيا
than any sex education programs ever had.
أكثر مما فعل أي برنامج تثقيفي متخصص للجنس.
All of those are gone.
وكل هذا قد إختفى .
We are squandering the most valuable resource
نحن نبدد أكثر الموارد قيمة
we have on this continent: the valuable resource
على هذه القارة, وهو مورد
of the imagination.
الخيال القيم.
In the film, "Sometimes in April" by Raoul Peck,
في فيلم "أحيانا في إبريل" ل"راؤول بيك"
Idris Elba is poised in a scene with his machete raised,
يقف "إدريس إلبا" في المشهد رافعا خنجره,
and he's being forced by a crowd to chop up his best friend --
وتضغط عليه الحشود ليقتل أعز أصدقائه--
fellow Rwandan Army officer, albeit a Tutsi --
وهو ضابط جيش رواندي, و إن كان من ال"توتسي"
played by Fraser James.
يلعب دوره "فرايزر جايمس".
And Fraser's on his knees, arms tied behind his back,
و فرايزر جالس على ركبتيه, زراعيه موثقتين خلف ظهره.
and he's crying.
وهو يبكي.
He's sniveling.
ينتحب.
It's a pitiful sight.
إنه منظر مؤثر.
And as we watch it, we are ashamed.
و نحن نشاهده, شعرنا بالخزي.
And we want to say to Idris, "Chop him up.
أردنا أن نقول لإدريس ,"إقتله.
Shut him up."
"إخرسه."
And as Idris moves, Fraser screams, "Stop!
و كما يتحرك إدريس, يصرخ فرايزر, "توقف!
Please stop!"
"أرجوك توقف!"
Idris pauses, then he moves again,
يتوقف إدريس, ثم يتحرك مرة أخرى,
and Fraser says, "Please!
و يقول فرايزر, "أرجوك!
Please stop!"
"أرجوك توقف!"
And it's not the look of horror and terror on Fraser's face that stops Idris or us;
و ليست نظرة الرعب و الخوف على وجه فرايزر هي التي أوقفت إدريس أو أوقفتنا؛
it's the look in Fraser's eyes.
إنها النظرة في عين فرايزر.
It's one that says, "Don't do this.
التي تقول, "لا تفعل هذا.
And I'm not saying this to save myself,
و أنا لا أقول هذا لأنقذ نفسي,
although this would be nice. I'm doing it to save you,
--بالرغم من ان ذلك سيكون لطيفا-- و لكني أقول هذا لأنقذك أنت,
because if you do this, you will be lost."
لأنك إذا فعلت هذا, ستفقد نفسك."
To be so afraid that you're standing in the face
أن تكون خائفا لأنك تواجه
of a death you can't escape and that you're soiling yourself
الموت الذي لا يمكنك الهروب منه, عادي أن تلطخ نفسك
and crying, but to say in that moment,
و أن تبكي و لكن أن تقول في تلك اللحظة
as Fraser says to Idris, "Tell my girlfriend I love her."
كما قال فرايزر لإدريس, "أخبر صديقتي أنني أحبها."
In that moment, Fraser says,
في تلك اللحظة يقول فرايزر,
"I am lost already, but not you ... not you."
لقد ضعت بالفعل, ولكن أنت لا..لا تضيع نفسك"
This is a redemption we can all aspire to.
هذا نوع من التوبة نتوق إليه جميعا.
African narratives in the West, they proliferate.
الروايات الأفريقية في الغرب في تزايد مستمر.
I really don't care anymore.
و لكني ما عدت أهتم بها.
I'm more interested in the stories we tell about ourselves --
أنا أهتم أكثر بالقصص التي نحكيها عن أنفسنا --
how as a writer, I find that African writers
كيف ككاتب, أجد أن الكُتاب الأفريقيين
have always been the curators of our humanity on this continent.
كانوا دوما القائمين أو الأوصياء على إنسانيتنا في هذه القارة.
The question is, how do I balance narratives that are wonderful
السؤال هو, كيف أوازن بين الروايات الرائعة
with narratives of wounds and self-loathing?
و الروايات المليئة بالجروح و إحتقار الذات؟
And this is the difficulty that I face.
و هذه هي العقبة التي تواجهني.
I am trying to move beyond political rhetoric
أحاول أن أتخطى الخطابة السياسية
to a place of ethical questioning.
إلى مكان حيث المسائلة الأخلاقية.
I am asking us to balance the idea
أطالب بأن نوازن بين فكرة
of our complete vulnerability with the complete notion
ضعفنا الكامل والمفهوم الكامل
of transformation of what is possible.
للتحول و الإمكانيات.
As a young middle-class Nigerian activist,
كناشط نيجيري صغير من عائلة متوسطة
I launched myself along with a whole generation of us
إندفعت مع جيل كامل
into the campaign to stop the government.
في حملة لإيقاف الحكومة
And I asked millions of people,
و طالبت الملايين من الناس,
without questioning my right to do so,
بدون أن يكون لي الحق في ذلك,
to go up against the government.
بأن يقفوا أمام الحكومة.
And I watched them being locked up in prison and tear gassed.
و وقفت أشاهد وهو يحبسون في السجن و يقذون بالغاز المسيل للدموع.
I justified it, and I said, "This is the cost of revolution.
و أبرر ذلك قائلا, "هذا هو ثمن الثورة.
Have I not myself been imprisoned?
"ألم أُسجن نفسي من قبل؟"
Have I not myself been beaten?"
"ألم أضرب أنا من قبل؟"
It wasn't until later, when I was imprisoned again,
و لم يكن إلا لاحقا, عندما سُجنت مرة أخري
that I understood the real meaning of torture,
عندما أدركت المعنى الحقيقي للعذاب,
and how easy your humanity can be taken from you,
و كيف يمكن أن تسلب منك إنسانيتك بسهولة,
for the time I was engaged in war,
لأن هذه المرة تدخلت في حرب,
righteous, righteous war.
حرب مبررة جدا.
Excuse me.
أعذروني.
Sometimes I can stand before the world --
أحيانا أستطيع أن اقف أمام العالم --
and when I say this, transformation
و في هذه الحالة التغيير
is a difficult and slow process --
هو عملية صعبة و بطيئة.--
sometimes I can stand before the world and say,
أحيانا أستطيع أن اقف أمام العالم و اقول,
"My name is Chris Abani.
" أسمي كريس أباني."
I have been human six days, but only sometimes."
" لقد كنت إنسانا ستة مرات. و لكن لبعض الوقت فقط."
But this is a good thing.
و لكن هذا شئ جيد.
It's never going to be easy.
ليس من المتوقع أن يكون الأمر سهلا.
There are no answers.
ليست الإجابت متوفرة.
As I was telling Rachel from Google Earth,
كما كنت أقول ل"رايتشل" من "جوجل إرث"
that I had challenged my students in America --
أني تحديت طلابي في أمريكا--
I said, "You don't know anything about Africa, you're all idiots."
قائلا, "أنتم لا تعلمون أي شئ عن أفريقيا, كلكم أغبياء."
And so they said, "Tell me about Africa, Professor Abani."
فكان ردهم, " إخبرنا عن أفريقيا, بروفيسور أباني."
So I went to Google Earth and learned about Africa.
فذهبت إلى موقع "جوجل إرث" و تعلمت عن افريقيا.
And the truth be told, this is it, isn't it?
و لنقول الحقيقة, هذا هو الأمر الواقع, أليس كذلك؟
There are no essential Africans,
لا يوجد هناك أفريقيين أصليين,
and most of us are as completely ignorant as everyone else
و معظمنا جاهلين تماما كالآخرين
about the continent we come from,
فيما يتعلق بالقارة التي أتينا منها,
and yet we want to make profound statements about it.
و مع ذلك نريد أن نتطلق تصريحات عميقة على لسانها.
And I think if we can just admit that we're all trying
و اعتقد إذا إستطعنا فقط أن نعترف أننا جميعا نحاول
to approximate the truth of our own communities,
أن نقرِب الحقيقة لمجتمعاتنا,
it will make for a much more nuanced
لينتج عنها مناقشات أكثر دقة
and a much more interesting conversation.
و أكثر إمتاعا بمراحل.
I want to believe that we can be agnostic about this,
أريد أن اصدق أنه في إمكاننا أن نكون جميعا ملحدين في هذا الشأن,
that we can rise above all of this.
لنرقى فوق كل ذلك التعصب.
When I was 10, I read James Baldwin's "Another Country,"
عندما كنت في العاشرة ,قرأت كتاب "دولة أخرى" ل"جايمس بالدوين"
and that book broke me.
و هذا الكتاب أثر في للغاية.
Not because I was encountering homosexual sex and love
ليس لأنها كانت المرة الأولى التي أصادف فيها
for the first time, but because the way James wrote about it
الحب و الجنس بين الشواذ و لكن بسبب الطريقة التي وصف بها جايمس الموضوع
made it impossible for me to attach otherness to it.
جعلت من الممكن بالنسبة لي أن أربطها بالغيرية.
"Here," Jimmy said.
"ها هو" قال جيمي.
"Here is love, all of it."
"ها هو الحب , كل ما فيه"
The fact that it happens in "Another Country"
و واقع أنها تحدث في "دولة أخرى"
takes you quite by surprise.
تصيبك بالمفاجأة.
My friend Ronald Gottesman says there are three kinds of people in the world:
صديقي "رونالد جوتسمان" يقول هناك ثلاثة أنواع من الأشخاص في العالم:
those who can count, and those who can't.
من يستطيع العد, ومن لا يستطيع.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
He also says that the cause of all our trouble
و يقول أيضا أن السبب الأساسي لكل مشاكلنا
is the belief in an essential, pure identity:
هو الإيمان بهوية أساسية خالصة:
religious, ethnic, historical, ideological.
دينية أو عرقية أو تاريخية أو إيديولوجية.
I want to leave you with a poem by Yusef Komunyakaa
أريد أن اودعكم بقصيدة ل "يوسف كومونياكا"
that speaks to transformation.
تتحدث عن التحول و التغيير.
It's called "Ode to the Drum," and I'll try and read it
تدعى "قصيدة للطبل", و سأحاول قرائتها
the way Yusef would be proud to hear it read.
بالطريقة التي تجعل يوسف فخورا بها.
"Gazelle, I killed you for your skin's exquisite touch,
"يا غزال, قتلتُكِ لملمس جلدك الرائع,
for how easy it is to be nailed to a board
لمدى سهولة تثبيته على لوحٍ
weathered raw as white butcher paper.
عُرِض للهواء حتى أصبح في بياض ورق الجزار.
Last night I heard my daughter praying for the meat here at my feet.
بالأمس سمعت إبنتي تدعو طلبا للحم هنا تحت قدميَ.
You know it wasn't anger that made me stop my heart till the hammer fell.
أتعلمين؟ لم يكن الغضب هو الذي جعلني أُسكت قلبي حتى وقعت عليك المطرقة.
Weeks ago, you broke me as a woman
منذ أسابيع, كسرتِني كإمرأةٍ
once shattered me into a song beneath her weight,
حطَمَتني ذات مرة إلى أغنية تحت وزن جسدها,
before you slouched into that grassy hush.
قبل أن تتهادي وسط همسات الأعشاب.
And now I'm tightening lashes, shaped in hide as if around a ribcage,
و الان أنا أشد الأسواط, أشكل الجلد كأنه حول قفصٍ صدري
shaped like five bowstrings.
في شكل خمسة أوتار.
Ghosts cannot slip back inside the body's drum.
فالأشباح لا تستطيع أن تعود في جسد طبلة.
You've been seasoned by wind, dusk and sunlight.
لقد طعَمتكِ الرياح, الغسق و ضوء الشمس.
Pressure can make everything whole again.
الضغط يجعل كل شئ صحيحا مرة أخرى,
Brass nails tacked into the ebony wood,
لتعلق مسامير النحاس في خشب الأبنوس
your face has been carved five times.
حُفر وجهك خمسة مرات.
I have to drive trouble in the hills.
يجب أن أقود ثورة في التلال.
Trouble in the valley,
ثورة في الوادي
and trouble by the river too.
و ثورة على ضفاف النهر أيضا.
There is no palm wine, fish, salt, or calabash.
فإنه لا يوجد نبيذ, سمك, ملح أو قرع الكالاباش.
Kadoom. Kadoom. Kadoom.
"كادوم, كادوم, كادوم.
Ka-doooom.
كادوووم.
Now I have beaten a song back into you.
و الآن وقد قرعت فيكي أغنية
Rise and walk away like a panther."
إنهضي و أمضي كالنمر."
Thank you.
شكراً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)